<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A warning piece to England, or, The wrath of God revealed against sinners his judgments being already entered upon the nation / by S.T.G.</title>
            <author>S. T. G., Lover of truth and peace.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1676</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 69 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 39 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A64265</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T59</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R184832</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12443809</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12443809</idno>
            <idno type="VID">62169</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A64265)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 62169)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 948:25)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A warning piece to England, or, The wrath of God revealed against sinners his judgments being already entered upon the nation / by S.T.G.</title>
                  <author>S. T. G., Lover of truth and peace.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 71, [3] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for D. Newman ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1676.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sin --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:62169:1"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:62169:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>A Warning Piece TO ENGLAND, OR THE WRATH of GOD Revealed againſt SINNERS, His Judgments being already entered upon the NATION.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> S. T. G.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A Lover of Peace and Truth.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 40. 10.</bibl>
               <p>I have not hid thy righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs within my Heart: I have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared thy faithfulneſs and thy Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, I have not concealed thy loving kindneſs, and thy truth from the great Congregation.</p>
            </q>
            <p>London, <hi>Printed for</hi> D. Newman <hi>at the Kings Arms in the Poultry,</hi> 1676.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:62169:2"/>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:62169:2"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Chriſtian Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>AS far as the Author knows his own heart, the main end of righting this ſmall Treatiſe, is that God may have all the glory; and this Sin ſinking Nation may have ſome benefit, and ſo undoubted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly they will if they hearken to Gods Counſel, to repent and turn from their evil ways to the Lord with their whole heart: the conſideration of the preſent con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed
<pb facs="tcp:62169:3"/>
ſtate of this poor Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, cauſed me ſeriouſly to mind the next way how they might be brought into a better condition; and I know no other way that God hath ſhewed us, but by humbling our ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lves before the Lord, to eſcape deſtruction and ruin. For God will not always bear, but then the Anger of the Lord will break forth in fury, if a people do not amend their ways and doings which are not good. God hath been earneſtly calling unto us, and lifting up his voice, and by his Word and Diſpenſations, perſwading us to return unto him. He hath tryed all ſorts and all ways, both Mercies and Judgments. Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="tcp:62169:3"/>
it is very ſad, that the hand of the Lord hath been ſo greatly lifted up, and that <hi>England</hi> ſhould be ſo blind, as not to take notice of his diſpleaſure, in afflicting us, with Sword, Pestilence and Fire, and threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Famine, but gratiouſly holding his hand, like a tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearted Father, unwilling to deſtroy us, except by our perſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting in Sin, we as it were force him utterly to conſume us from the face of the Earth. I humbly beſeech you ſeriouſly to read and ponder, what is ſaid in this little Book. And let not Satan perſwade you to throw off thoſe wholſom Exhortations, and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions contained therein. So
<pb facs="tcp:62169:4"/>
with my earneſt prayers at the Throne of Grace, for Rulers and Ruled, that the God of all Grace and Mercy would enable us to ſee the filthy nature of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Sin, to repent of all our falſe ways, as <hi>David</hi> ſaith in in the 119. <hi>Pſal. Through thy Precepts I get Underſtanding therefore I hate every falſe way.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>I remain thine in all truth and righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs. <hi>S. T.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:62169:4"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A Warning piece to</hi> England; <hi>or the wrath of God reveal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed againſt Sinners, his judgment being already entred upon the Nation.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>IT is very certain, out of the Scriptures of truth, that ſin brings the judgment of the great God upon Nations, Families, and Perſons; Sin crys aloud for Vengeance, Wrath, and Deſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, upon wicked and ungodly men<hi>:</hi> Oh! let every one ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly conſider the dreadful effects of ſin; it deſtroyed the old world, <hi>Gen.</hi> 6. 5, 6, 7. <hi>And God ſaw that the wickedneſs of man was great</hi>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:62169:5"/>
               <hi>in the Earth, and that every Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gination of his heart was only Evil continually.</hi> Verſ. the 6. <hi>And it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pented the Lord that he made man on the Earth, and it grieved him at his heart.</hi> Verſ. the 7. <hi>And the Lord ſaid, I will deſtroy man, whom I have created, from the face of the Earth, both man and beaſt, and the creeping thing, and the fouls of the air: for it repenteth me that I have made man.</hi> Likewiſe thoſe five Citys in the plain, were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed by fire. <hi>Gen.</hi> 18. 20. <hi>And the Lord ſaid, becauſe the cry of</hi> Sodom <hi>is great, and becauſe their Sin is very grievous.</hi> Chap. the 19. 24, 25. <hi>Then the Lord rained upon</hi> Sodom, <hi>and upon</hi> Gomorrah, <hi>brimſtone and fire from the Lord out of heaven; he overthrew thoſe Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tys, and all the plains, and all the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants of the Citys, and that which grew upon the ground.</hi> Conſider what deſolations and depopulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:62169:5"/>
ſin did bring upon Gods be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved People, as you may read <hi>Lament.</hi> 1. 2, 3, 4, 5, 7, 8. ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes. <hi>She weepeth ſore in the night, and her tears are on her cheeks; a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong all her Lovers ſhe hath none to comfort her; all her friends have dealt treacherouſly with her, they are become her enemies.</hi> Judah <hi>is gon in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to captivity, becauſe of affliction, and becauſe of great ſervitude; ſhe dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth among the Heathen, and ſhe find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth no reſt; all her perſecutors over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>took her between the ſtraits; the ways of</hi> Sion <hi>do mourn becauſe none come to her ſolemn feaſts: All her Gates are deſolate; her prieſts ſigh, her virgins are afflicted, and ſhe is in bitterneſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Her adverſaries are the chief, and her enemies proſper, for the Lord hath afflicted her for the multitude of her tranſgreſſions, her children are gone into captivity before the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy: and from the Daughter of</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:62169:6"/>
Sion <hi>all her Beauty is departed, her Princes are become like Harts that find no Paſture, and they are gon without ſtrength before the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Jeruſalem <hi>remembred in the days of affliction and of her miſeries, all her pleaſant things that ſhe had in the days of old, when her People fell into the hand of the enemy, and none did help her, the Adverſaries ſaw her, and did mock at her Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baths;</hi> Jeruſalem <hi>hath grievouſly ſined, therefore ſhe is removed; all that honoured her, deſpiſe her, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they have ſeen her Nakedneſs, yea, ſhe ſighed and turned backward; her filthyneſs is in her skirts, ſhe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membreth not her laſt end: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſhe came down wonderfully, ſhe had no comforter.</hi> Chapt. the 2. 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6. verſes, and 3, 4, 5. Chapters of the book of the <hi>Lamenta.</hi> as in the 5. Chapt. 16, verſ. <hi>The Crown is fallen from</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:62169:6"/>
               <hi>the head, and wo to us that we have ſined.</hi> I might multiply Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures to ſhew the diſpleaſure of God againſt Tranſgreſſors, and after thoſe many premonitions when they would not be forwarn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, God caſt them off, making them a by-word to all the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons round about, Oh <hi>England,</hi> hear and tremble, for the fiery anger of the Lord will burn like an Oven, and none ſhall be able to quench it, ſee <hi>Malachi</hi> 4. 1. <hi>For behold the day cometh that ſhall burn as an Oven, and all the proud, yea, and all they that do wickedly ſhall be ſtubble, and the day that cometh ſhall burn them up, ſaith the Lord of hoſts, that it ſhall leave them neither root nor branch.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Qu. <hi>What ſins bring National judgments?</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> 1. Slighting and reject<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Law and the Prophets, and eſpecially Jeſus Chriſt in the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:62169:7"/>
time of the Goſpel. 2. The ſins of Rulers. 3. Idolatry. 4. Adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery, 5. Pride, 6. Swearing and Curſing. 7. Murder. 8. Drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenneſs and exceſs.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Sin.</hi> Slighting the Law and the Prophets, which God com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plains of in the 1. of <hi>Eſ.</hi> 2, 3, 4. <hi>verſ. I have nouriſhed and brought up a People, but they have rebelled againſt me. The Ox know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth his owner, and the Aſs his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters Crib, but Iſrael hath not known me. Ah ſinful Nation, a people la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den with iniquity, a ſeed of evil do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, children that have corrupted themſelves.</hi> So the judgments are threatned in the enſuing ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and God makes very great complaints of them, in ſeveral of the Prophets, as <hi>Jer.</hi> and <hi>Ezek.</hi> &amp;c. and they proceeded to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject Jeſus Chriſt in the Goſpel, and this is a very great ſin, and brings deſolation upon all thoſe to
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:62169:7"/>
whom it is ſent, and they reject it. <hi>Heb.</hi> 2. 2, 3. <hi>How ſhall we e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcape, if we neglect ſo great Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on:</hi> and when <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſlighted Jeſus Chriſt and his words, they were left to the hardnes of their hearts, and the blindneſs of their minds, <hi>That hearing they ſhall hear, and not underſtand, and ſeeing they ſhall ſee, and not perceive,</hi> and then God wholly left them, and ſent his Miniſters to the Gentiles; Lo we turn to the Gentiles ſaith the Apoſtle.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Sin.</hi> Is the ſins of Rulers, as <hi>David</hi> numbring the People. Sometimes God plagues the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple for the Rulers ſake. 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 24. 11, 12. <hi>The word of God came to Gad the Seer, ſaying, go and ſay unto David, thus ſaith the Lord, I offer thee three things, chooſe thee one of them, that I may do it unto thee,</hi> verſ. the 13. <hi>So Gad came to David and told him, and ſaid, ſhall</hi>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:62169:8"/>
                  <hi>ſeven years of Famin come untothee, in thy Land, or wilt thou flee three Months before thy enemies while they purſue thee: or that there be three days peſtilence in thy Land,</hi> verſ. the 15. <hi>So the Lord ſent a peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence upon Iſrael from morning even to the time appointed, and there dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of the people from Dan to Beer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheba, ſeventy thouſand men.</hi> Now God plagues a people for the ſins of the Rulers, eſpecially when the people follow the ſinful examples of Rulers. Oh my people they that lead thee cauſe thee to err, as <hi>Jeroboam</hi> the Son of <hi>Nebat,</hi> which made <hi>Iſrael</hi> to ſin, which was a great brand of infamy, recorded to after ages; ſo <hi>Ahab,</hi> that ſold himſelf to do wickedneſs, and <hi>Manaſſeth,</hi> and all thoſe wicked Kings that provoked the Lord, 2 <hi>King.</hi> 21. from the 9. to the 14 verſ. to bring deſolation up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the people; <hi>Oh then let Rulers</hi>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:62169:8"/>
                  <hi>be wiſe and ſerve the Lord with fear. Kiſs the Son leſt he be angry, and ye periſh from the right way; if once his wrath be kindled but alittle, bleſſed are they that put their truſt in him. Pſal.</hi> 2. 10, 11, 12. Let all therefore conſider, both Rulers and Ruled in this Nation, that if God ſpared not the old world, nor thoſe citys in the plain that were deſtroyed by fire, nor his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved people <hi>Iſrael</hi> when they ſined againſt him, how then can <hi>England</hi> eſcape when they follow the ſame way of ſining, nothing can be expected but deſolation, God can quickly hiſs for his three executioners, which are the ſword, peſtilence, and Famin.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Sin.</hi> Is Idolatry, which ſtrikes at the very Being of God; how full of wrath was God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Iſrael</hi> for their Idolatry. 3. <hi>Iudg.</hi> 7, 8. <hi>and the Children of Iſrael did evil in the ſight of the</hi>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:62169:9"/>
                  <hi>Lord, and forgat the Lord their God, and ſerved Baalim and the Groves; therefore the anger of the Lord was hot againſt Iſrael, and he ſold them into the hand of Cuſhan-Riſhathaim King of Meſopotamia. Deut.</hi> 13. 2, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10. with diverſe other places which I ſhall not mention, becauſe it will make it larger than I intend this Warning-piece.</p>
               <p>But certainly Idolatry is a land-deſtroying ſin, which above all ſins will draw down the wrath of God upon a Nation to root it out, and utterly to deſtroy it, for he is jealous of his name, and his glory will he not give to another, not his praiſe to graven Images.</p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>Sin.</hi> Is Pride. Here I might write a large volumn; but to omit ſeveral particulars in relation to this ſin, I ſhall ſpeak of that which is more obvious to the ſence, as firſt Pride in apparel. Can the oldeſt man remember ſuch ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:62169:9"/>
of apparel, eſpecially in this great City, yet notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the eminent hand of the great God hath been ſo lately upon them, that moſt part of this City was conſumed into aſhes, that the inhabitants are but poor to what they have been heretofore, yet what a fair outſide do they make when the Nation is ſinking. Oh what horrible folly is this, it is like one that Paints his pots and trims up his ſhop, and ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dainly it is ſhutup. Secondly pride in their houſes, in their furniture; and how coſtly is it, with very much exceſs, ſo that the ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluities in clothing, and dyet, and furniture, would refreſh the bowels of the poor which are ſome of them ready to periſh for want of bread; few ſeriouſly conſider the great diſtreſſes and wants of the poor; ſome that heretofore could have admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:62169:10"/>
to the neceſsities of others, are forced to beg their bread; conſider what God ſaith in the 2. of <hi>Iſaiah</hi> from the 10. to the 18. verſ. <hi>Enter into the rock, and hide thee in the duſt for fear of the Lord, and the glory of his Majeſly; The lof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty looks ſhall be humbled, and the haughtineſs of men ſhall be bowed down, and the Lord alone ſhall be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alted in that day; for the day of the Lord of Hoſts ſhall be upon every one that is proud &amp; lofty, &amp; every one that is lifted up, &amp; he ſhall be brought low, and upon all the Cedars of Leba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non that are high and lifted up, and upon all the Oaks of Baſhan; &amp; upon all the high Mountains that are lif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted up, &amp; upon every tower, and upon every fenced wall, and upon all the ſhips of Tarſhiſh, and upon all the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant pictures: verſ.</hi> the 17. <hi>And the loftineſs of man ſhall be bowed down, &amp; the haughtineſs of man ſhall be laid low, and the Lord alone ſhall be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alted</hi>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:62169:10"/>
                  <hi>in that day. Chapt.</hi> the 3 <hi>from</hi> the 16. to the end. <hi>Moreover the Lord ſaith, becauſe the Daughters of Sion are haughty, and walk with ſtret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched forth necks and wanton eyes, wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king and mincing as they go, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king a tinkling with their feet. verſ.</hi> the 17. <hi>The Lord will ſmite with a ſcab the crown of the head of the Daughters of Sion; In that day the Lord will take away the bravery of their tinkling ornaments about their feet, and their cauls, and their round tires like the Moon &amp;c. verſ.</hi> 26. <hi>And her gates ſhall lament, and ſhe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing deſolate ſhall ſit upon the ground.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The 5. Sin is <hi>Swearing</hi> and <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwearing,</hi> likewiſe <hi>Curſing,</hi> which are Sins of a very high nature, very much diſpleaſing to the great God, and provoke him to bring ſwift judgment upon the Nation; eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially that wicked diveliſh Oath of the Dam'es, that deſire God to damn their ſouls, whereas God
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:62169:11"/>
and Jeſus Chriſt would have them to be ſaved. See the 1 of Timoth. 2. 4. <hi>Who will have all men to be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, and to come to the knowledg of the truth.</hi> Doſt thou deſire God to damn thee; oh poor miſerable Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, that my heart could bleed for thee that art ſo ignorant; doſt thou conſider what it is to be damn'd; to be damn'd, is to be ſeparated from the preſence of the Lord and the glory of his Majeſty, and for ever to be caſt into that lake that burneth with fire and brim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone, in thoſe eaſeleſs, endleſs, &amp; remedileſs torments, where there is weeping and gnaſhing of teeth. Math. 25. 41. <hi>Then ſhall he ſay alſo unto them on the left hand, depart from me ye curſed into everlaſting fire, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for the Devil and his Angels:</hi> Iſa. 66. 24. <hi>And they ſhall go forth and look upon the carkaſes of thoſe that tranſgreſs'd againſt me; for their worm ſhall not die, neither ſhall their</hi>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:62169:11"/>
                  <hi>ſire be quench'd, and they ſhall be an abhorring to all fleſh.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. Vain <hi>Swearing,</hi> when men ſo commonly ſwear that they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ordinarily diſcourſe but they muſt ſwear; nay it is the faſhion to ſwear, and if a man cannot ſwear, he is not fit company for ſome Gentlemen. Oh poor miſerable man, is it thy common practice &amp; delight to blaſpheme and take the great and dreadful name of God in vain. Oh what wilt thou do when thou ſhalt appear before him at the laſt Day, as thou certainly muſt; ſurely thou wilt tremble, &amp; deſire <hi>mountains and rocks to fall upon thee, to hide thee from him that ſitteth upon the throne, and from the Lamb; Revel.</hi> 6. 16. See thoſe Scriptures that prohibit vain <hi>Swearing,</hi> James 5. 12. <hi>But above all things, my bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, ſwear not, neither by Heaven, neither by the Earth, neither by any other Oath; but let your yea, be yea,</hi>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:62169:12"/>
                  <hi>and your nay nay, leſt ye fall into con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation.</hi> Mat. 5. from the 33 to the 38 verſes. Surely ſuch words are nothing but the ſpeakings of the Devil in thee.</p>
               <p n="2">2 Sort of ſwearing is for-ſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring thy ſelf when thou art call'd before a Magiſtrate; this is a great ſin, that brings judgments upon the Nation; for oaths the Land mourns. How many poor crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures are hired to for-ſwear them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and how many do it to pleaſure great men; and others wickedly for-ſwear themſelves for to get their Neighbours goods, and to defraud their neighbour of his right. Levit. 6. 3, 4, 5. chap. 5. 1. Jere. 23. 10. <hi>For the land is full of Adulterers; for becauſe of ſwearing the land mourneth, the pleaſant places of the wilderneſs are driedup, and their courſe is evil, and their force is not right:</hi> Hoſe. 4. 1, 2. <hi>Hear ye the word of the Lord ye children of Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el,</hi>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:62169:12"/>
                  <hi>tel: for the Lord hath a controverſie with the inhabitants of the land, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there is no truth, nor mercy, nor knowledg of God in the land. By ſwearing, and lying, and killing, and ſtealing, and committing Adultery, they break out, and blood toucheth blood.</hi> Chap. 10. verſ. 4. <hi>They have ſpoken words, ſwearing falſly in making a covenant.</hi> Zach. 5. 3, 4. Mal. 3. 5. <hi>And I will come near to you in judgment, and will be a ſwift witneſs againſt the Sorcerers, and againſt the Adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, and againſt the falſe Swearers.</hi> Doubtleſs this is a very great ſin, that brings judgment upon the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, families and perſons.</p>
               <p n="3">3. That wicked ſin of Curſing, parents curſing their children, &amp; ſervants; ſome children curſe their parents, ſervants curſe their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters. Nay I have heard wicked men curſe themſelves &amp; their cat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tel.
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:62169:13"/>
Oh how common is it for men to bid the pox take them. Fooliſh, ignorant perſons, they cry out with pain and anguiſh, &amp; ſeveral of them yeild up the ghoſt, and if they do not repent, go quick down to hell: they that curſe themſelves and their cattel, at laſt bring a curſe upon all they have. Math. 15. 4, <hi>For God commanded ſaying, honour thy Father and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and he that curſeth Father or Mother, let him die the death.</hi> Rom. 3. 14, 15, 16, <hi>Whoſe mouth is full of curſing, deſtruction and miſery are in their ways, and the way of peace have they not known:</hi> vers the 18, <hi>There is no fear of God before their eyes. Jame.</hi> 3. 10, <hi>Out of the ſame mouth, proceedeth bleſsing and curſing: my brethren theſe things ought not ſo to be.</hi> Several other places of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture I might produce, but theſe may ſuffice. Oh what mad blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs is this, that rational men, and
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:62169:13"/>
thoſe that have lived under the ſound of the Goſpel ſo long, ſhou'd be ſo ignorant and wicked, as to deſire the plagues of God to be poured upon them and theirs. Oh that my head was water, and my eyes a fountain of tears, that I might weep night and day for the ſins and ſorrows of poor diſtreſſed ſin-ſinking England.</p>
               <p>7. Sin is Adultery, and had I time and a heart, I might be very large to enumerate the multitude of tranſgreſſions of this nature, &amp; ſurely this ſin is grown ſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, that it is open before the Sun, and men plead for it, and ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry much extrenuate it. Nay I que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion whether ſome are not ſo no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toriouſly wicked to urge Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture for their abominable unclean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. Know O thou prophane A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſt, the Scriptures give thee no liberty, but will judg thee for thy ſins at the laſt and great day of
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:62169:14"/>
account; when you ſhall certainly give an account for all your acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons done in the body; and how will you anſwer the taking your neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours wife from him; it may be thou wilt inſtance <hi>David's</hi> adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery; but conſider if thou wilt commit <hi>David's</hi> ſin, then thou muſt expect <hi>David's</hi> puniſhment, which was very ſevere. See Pſal. the 32, from the 1, to the 6, verſ. verſ. the 3, <hi>When I kept ſilence, my bones waxed old, through my roaring all the day long.</hi> verſ. the 4, <hi>For day &amp; night thy hand was heavy upon me; my moiſture is turned into the drought of ſummer.</hi> verſ. the 5. <hi>I acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg my ſin unto thee, and mine iniquity have I not hid: I ſaid I will confeſs my tranſgreſsions unto the Lord, and thou forgaveſt the iniquity of my ſin.</hi> Pſal. 51. from 1, to the 13. verſ. <hi>Have mercy upon me O God accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to thy loving kindneſs, according to the multitude of thy tender mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies,</hi>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:62169:14"/>
                  <hi>blot out all my tranſgreſsions:</hi> verſ. the 2. <hi>waſh me throughly from mine iniquity, and cleanſe me from my ſin; for I acknowledge my tranſgreſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and my ſin is ever before me.</hi> verſ. the 4. <hi>Againſt thee only have I ſinned, and done this evil in thy ſight, that thou mighteſt be juſtified when thou ſpeakeſt, and clear when thou judgeſt:</hi> verſ. 5. <hi>Behold, I am ſhapen in iniquity, and in ſin did my Mother conceive me.</hi> verſ. the 7. <hi>Purge me with hyſſop, and I ſhall be clean; waſh me, and I ſhall be whiter than ſnow. Make me to hear joy and gladneſs, that the bones that thou haſt broken may rejoice.</hi> verſ. the 9. <hi>Hide thy face from my ſins, and blot out all mine iniquities.</hi> verſ. 10. <hi>Create in me a clean heart, O God, and renew a right ſpirit within me.</hi> verſ. 11. <hi>Caſt me not out of thy preſence, and take not thy holy Spirit from me.</hi> verſ. 12. <hi>Reſtore to me the joy of thy ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, and uphold me with thy free</hi>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:62169:15"/>
                  <hi>Spirit.</hi> See what miſery this ſin of Adultery brought upon King <hi>David,</hi> that made him cry out in the bitterneſs of his ſoul, and all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt brought him to the grave. For his radical moiſture was tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned into the drought of the ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer. Surely ſin brings death, both a natural, ſpiritual, and eternal, <hi>The wages of ſin is death,</hi> Rom. 7. 23. without true unfeigned repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, and turning from it as <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> did. But how many perplexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of heart had he, and how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny chaſtiſements were inflicted upon him, driven from his king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom; he that came out off his own bowels, roſe up againſt him, the hearts of the people were aliena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from him. 2 Sam. 15. from the 13. to the 18. verſ. 23, 30. And ſo you ſee his great diſtreſs, by reaſon of thoſe ſins of Murder and Adultery; and in his flight he was ſo deſpiſed, that <hi>Shimei,</hi> one of
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:62169:15"/>
his Subjects curſed him, and threw ſtones at him, chapt. 16. from the 5 verſ. to the 9. O the confuſion and diſtreſs that ſin brings upon a people, &amp; how fooliſh are the Sons and Daughters of men, to delight in that which will utterly deſtroy them both ſoul and body; and hate thoſe things that would preſerve them in peace and proſperity; that is, they hate Chriſt and his ways and people. Prov. 8. 35, 36. <hi>For who ſo findeth me findeth life, and ſhall obtain favour of the Lord.</hi> verſ. 36. <hi>But he that ſinneth againſt me, wrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth his own ſoul: all they that hate me love death.</hi> Very well may wicked men be call'd in the Scriptures mad men and fools, becauſe they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy themſelves, and eſteem of things of no value, more than thoſe things that are exceeding pretious, &amp; to be moſt highly valued in the ſuperlative degree. So God com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plains of the people of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> in
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:62169:16"/>
the 5 of Jer. 8, 9. <hi>They were as fed horſes, in the morning every one neighed after his neighbours wife; ſhall I not viſit for theſe things ſaith the Lord; ſhall not my ſoul be avenged on ſuch a Nation as this.</hi> Several o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Scriptures I might produce which declare the wrath of God againſt a ſinful people, that will not be perſwaded to break off their ſins by repentance. O conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der how many rules thou breakeſt by committing this ſin of Adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and Fornication. 1 The 7. Command. Thou ſhalt not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit Adultery. 2 the 10 Com. Thou ſhalt not covet thy Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour's wife. 3. The rule of Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, that Royal rule. Do as thou wouldſt be don by. Would you be contented that another ſhould take your wife and defile her, why then will you be ſo injurious to your neighbour, as to covet that which is none of yours, contrary to the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:62169:16"/>
rule of God's holy word. Jer. 5. 9, 10, 11. <hi>For the houſe of Iſrael, and the houſe of Judah, have dealt treacherouſly againſt me, ſaith the Lord; they have belied the Lord, and ſaid it is not he, neither ſhall evil come upon us, neither ſhall we ſee ſword nor famin.</hi> verſ. 13. <hi>And the Prophets ſhall become wind, and the word is not in them; thus ſhall it be don unto them.</hi> verſ. 14. <hi>Wher<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>fore thus ſaith the Lord of hoſts, becauſe ye ſpeak this word, behold I will make my words in thy mouth fire, and this people wood, and it ſhall devour them.</hi> verſ. 15. <hi>Loe I will bring a Nation upon you from far, O houſe of Iſrael, ſaith the Lord: it is a mighty Nation, it is an ancient Nation, whoſe lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage thou knoweſt not, neither un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandeſt what they ſay.</hi> verſ. 21. <hi>Hear now this O fooliſh people, and without underſtanding, which have eyes and ſee not, ears and hear not,</hi> verſ. 22. <hi>Fear ye not me? ſaith the</hi>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:62169:17"/>
                  <hi>Lord, will ye not tremble at my pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence? which have placed the ſand for the bound of the Sea by a perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al decree that it cannot paſs, though the waves thereof toſs themſelves, yet can they not prevail; though they roar, yet cannot they paſs over it;</hi> and ſo to the end of the chap. verſ. 28. <hi>They are waxen fat, they ſhine, yea they overpaſs the deeds of the wicked, they judge not the cauſe of the father<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, yet they proſper, and the right of the needy do they not judge.</hi> verſ. 29. <hi>Shall I not viſit for theſe things, ſaith the Lord? ſhall not my ſoul be aven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged of ſuch a Nation as this?</hi> verſ. 30. <hi>A wonderful and horrible thing is committed in the land.</hi> verſ. 31. <hi>The Prophets prophecy falſly and the Prieſts bear rule by their means, and my people love to have it ſo, and what will ye do in the end thereof.</hi> And thus you ſee how ſin provokes the Lord to deſtroy Nations, Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies and Perſons. Thou that
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:62169:17"/>
art ſo injurious to take away thy Neighbours wife, God doth ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny times take away all that ſuch wicked perſons have, and they are brought to a morſel of bread. <hi>For a whore is a deep ditch, and a ſtrange woman a narrow pit.</hi> Prov. 23. 27, 28, 29. <hi>She lyeth allſo in wait as for a prey, and increaſeth tranſgreſsours among men. Who hath wo? who hath ſorrow? who hath contention? who hath babling? who hath wounds with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out cauſe? who hath redneſs of eyes?</hi> Surely Whoremongers and Adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terers God will judge, even in this life without true repentance, and aſſuredly in the life to come. It is very ſad to ſee the impudence of the femal ſex. How many of them have harlots behaviour<hi>:</hi> yea Profeſſours, and thoſe that would be thought ſober women; yet go naked-neck'd from ſhoulder to ſhoulder, and their breſts ſeen which parts ſhould be covered in
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:62169:18"/>
modeſty, and that becauſe it is the faſhion, and their Relations go ſo<hi>:</hi> &amp; this is their fooliſh excuſe, that when they come among them, they ſhall be contemned by them: no matter, for it is but by the wantons and Hectours of this age. Drunkards count ſuch as will be drunk with them, honeſt men and Good-fellows; but they are ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the honeſter for their eſteem. Away then with the nakedneſs and cover your breſts and ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders for ſhame, or elſe what ever ſhew of modeſty thou makeſt, it will be eſteemed by ſober perſons vain and fooliſh. And ſeeing thou giveſt way to uncover thy naked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and ſo allureſt wicked men, thou mayſt be overcome at laſt by lewd men to commit the ſin of uncleanneſs. O avoid all appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of evil; for Chriſtians are to be adorned with modeſty, &amp; to uſe ſobriety in all their actions. O
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:62169:18"/>
poor vile ſinner, thou that excu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt thy ſelf, by being a great man or woman in this world, and therefore thou muſt not be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouled: what art thou, but a lump of clay, a heap of ſinful duſt and aſhes? That is but a greater aggravation of thy condemnation, for the more mercies thou haſt received from God, the greater is thy Puniſhment; if thou abuſeſt theſe good mercies of God, as riches, honour, that thou receiveſt from his bountiful hand more than others: and becauſe it is more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emplary and prevalent to draw others, therefore it is accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied with more aggravations: in regard thou receiveſt more kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs from God than others, and ſo takeſt God's weapons to fight againſt him. How canſt thou eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cape great condemnation, that ſinneſt againſt ſo much light and ſo much love. Oh fooliſh and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe;
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:62169:19"/>
do ye thus provoke the Lord to bring judgment and deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, until he hath conſumed you from of the earth. <hi>Job,</hi> 24. 15. <hi>The eye alſo of the Adulterer watcheth for the twilight, ſaying no eye ſhall ſee me, and diſguiſeth his face,</hi> 16, 17, 18, verſ. Jer. 10. 11. <hi>For the land is full of Adulterers, for becauſe of Swearing the land mourneth; the pleaſant places of the wilderneſs are dried up, their courſe is evil, and their force is not right,</hi> Mala. 3. 5. <hi>And I will come near to you in judgment, and will be a ſwift witneſs againſt the Sorcerers, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Adulterers, and againſt falſe Swearers, and againſt thoſe that oppreſs the hireling of his wages, the widow, and the fatherleſs, and turn aſide the ſtranger from his right, and fear not me, ſaith the Lord of hoſts.</hi> And thus you may ſee, how God doth threaten judgments a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt theſe ſins, and againſt all
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:62169:19"/>
ſin: likewiſe ſee what the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> ſaith in 1, <hi>Corin.</hi> 6. 9, 10. <hi>Be not deceived, neither Fornicators, nor Idolaters, nor Adulterers, nor Effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minate, nor abuſers of themſelves with mankind; nor Theeves, nor Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetous, nor Drunkards, nor Extor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioners, ſhall inherit the Kingdom of God.</hi> So Heb. 13. 4. <hi>Marriage is honourable in all; but Whoremongers and Adulterers God will judge.</hi> Rev. 22. 15. <hi>For without are Dogs, Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerers, and Whoremongers, Murde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, and Idolaters, and whoſoever loveth and maketh a lye.</hi> I beſeech you conſider ſeriouſly, what God would have you, in theſe Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures; for they are ſharply repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hending your ſins. You that are guilty of theſe abominations take heed; for it is a fearful thing to fall into the hands of the great and dreadful God, who will be a conſuming fire to all rebellious ſinners. <hi>Pſa.</hi> 50. 22. <hi>Now conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:62169:20"/>
                  <hi>this ye that forget God, leſt I tear you in pieces, and there be none to deliver.</hi> Oh let thy heart tremble within thee, when thou conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt that although thou art in thy ſecret chamber with thy minion, yet God ſeeth all thy wickedneſs, and will judge thee at the laſt and great day of accompt, when all the Adulterers and Adultreſſes ſhall deſire the rocks and mountains to fall upon them to hide them from him that ſits upon the throne, and ſhall not have ſo much favour, but ſhall be ſeverely judged and condemned, and caſt into the lake that burneth with fire and brim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone, in thoſe endleſs, eaſl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſs and remedileſs torments.</p>
               <p>7. Land deſtroying Sin is mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, this is a great crying Sin, that cryes aloud for vengeance, upon the Perſons that are guilty, and thoſe that paſs by willful Murther and upon all thoſe Juries, that
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:62169:20"/>
find many Murders but man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlaughter, ſurely this Sin of mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der is frequently committed in this great City and Suburbs, and in all other parts of the Nation; what a horrible ſhame is it, that the City of <hi>London</hi> and <hi>Weſtmin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,</hi> that ſhould be the beſt go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verned, being the chief place of the Nation, that there ſhould be ſo many outrages committed, where the Goſpel is ſo power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully preached, beyond all the places in the World; that which God hath ſo much prohibited in his holy word, Exod. 20. 13. <hi>Thou ſhalt not kill.</hi> Gen. 1. 9, 6. <hi>Whoſo ſheddeth mans blood, by man ſhall his blood be ſhed, for in the Im<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ge of God made he man;</hi> which is given as a reaſon of this prohibition, and this is confirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Lord Jeſus. Matth. 5. 21, 22. Chapt. 19. 18. <hi>thou ſhalt do no Murther, thou ſhalt not Steal,</hi>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:62169:21"/>
                  <hi>thou ſhalt not bear falſe Witneſs, &amp;c.</hi> See Num. 35. 16. <hi>And if he ſmite him with an Inſtrument of Iron ſo that he dy, he is a Murther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and the Murtherer ſhall ſurely be put to death.</hi> verſ. the 31. <hi>More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over ye ſhall take no ſatisfaction for the Life of the Murtherer which is guilty of Death, but he ſhall ſurely be put to Death.</hi> verſ. the 30. <hi>who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo killeth any perſon ſhall be put to Death by the mouth of his Witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes.</hi> Oh the corruption of this wicked age, that if a man be a great man, or have great Friends, or a plentiful Purſe, how is ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice apt to be perverted; and it may be the Proſecutor a poor man, how ſhall he be brow-beaten, and not ſuffered to ſpeak, if the Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therer be in his drink, or be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtempered, there will be ſome excuſe or other made for him; Oh do not think theſe poor ſorry excuſes will ſerve you, be not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:62169:21"/>
God is not mocked, that which you ſow, you ſhall reap to your great ſorrow, and thoſe that are inſtrumental in ſaving Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therers, from the higheſt to the loweſt you ſhall ſmart for it, when a Gentleman hath commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted or Murthered a Man, he flyes to <hi>France,</hi> and then his Friends procure a Pardon, or elſe the Judge and Jury muſt be ſpoken unto, and I wiſh they do not find plain Murther is Manſlaughter, eſpecially if he be a Couſin, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated to a great man, what ſhifts will there be to ſave this Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therers Life, and it may be inſtead of repenting, this Hector goes and kills another man, judge you who kill<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>d that man, whoſoever it be that ſaves a Murtherer un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtly, I muſt needs be plain with you, and declare unto you that the wrath of God is againſt all un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſneſs: and thou Sinner,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:62169:22"/>
by ſinning againſt God, treaſureſt up wrath againſt the day of wrath and revelation of the righteous Judgements of God, who will reward every man according to his works. <hi>Rom.</hi> 2. 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10, 11, 12.</p>
               <p>8 <hi>Sin,</hi> is Drunkenneſs and exceſs, this is a beaſtly ſwiniſh ſin; what to take thoſe creatures which God hath graciouſly given to ſatisfy and refreſh Nature, thou by taking exceſs doſt expreſs and deſtroy Nature. Oh how fooliſh and unwiſe are poor deſperate ſinners, that by your practice, ſpeak forth as if God had made you to drink and ſwill and take your fill, till you diſgorge your ſelves, and be an anuſance and diſturbance to all ſober per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons near you, nay ſure God hath made you for more noble ends, <hi>viz.</hi> to glorify him, and to know your intereſt in him, and to do
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:62169:22"/>
good in your Generation; what benefit is a Drunkard to Church or Common-wealth, nay he is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry injurious to himſelf, his Family and all other ſober good men, that cannot endure to ſee God diſhonoured and his good mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies abuſed, Oh what great ſhame is this, that where the Goſpel is ſo powerfully preached, and ſo much light, that ſuch an abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable vice as this ſhould reign and be ſo frequently practiſed, that is againſt the very light of Nature. I might be long upon this ſubject to ſhew you the ſad effects of this beaſtly Sin of drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenneſs, what a big bellyed Sin is this, which is an occaſion ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times of Murther and uncleanneſs, when men are deprived of their reaſon, then they are mad, and ſit for any miſchief to themſelves &amp; others, ſome men when they are drunk have broken their Necks
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:62169:23"/>
off their Horſes, fallen down off ſome ſteep place, not being able to ſtand, and ſo deſtroyed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, others committing un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleanneſs, Raviſhing their Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours Wives and their Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, many ſad effects doth this ſin of drunkenneſs produce; it fits men to do all manner of evil, and unfits them for any thing that is good, either for Soul or body. Now I ſhall ſhew you the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures wherein the great God pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibits this beaſtly Sin, to ſee that if by any means you may be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed upon to leave this ſilthy dirty abominable Sin. See Eſ. 5. 11. <hi>Wo to them that riſe up ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the morning and follow ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drink, that continue till night, till wine inflame them.</hi> verſ. 22. <hi>Wo to them that are mighty to drink wine, and men of ſtrength to mingle ſtrong-drink.</hi> verſ. 23, 24. Chap. 56. 12. Mica. 2. 11. Nah. 1. 10.
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:62169:23"/>
                  <hi>For while they be folded together as thorns, and while they are drunken as drunkards they ſhall be devoured as ſtubble fully dry.</hi> Joel. the 5. <hi>Awake ye Drunkards, weep and howl all ye Drinkers of Wine.</hi> 1. Cor. 6. 9, 10. <hi>Be not deceived, neither Fornicators, nor Idolators, nor A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulterers, nor Effeminate, nor A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſers of themſelves with Man-kind, nor Thieves, nor Covetous, nor Revellers, nor extortioners ſhall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herit the Kingdom of God.</hi> Eſ. 19, 14, Luk. 21. 34, 35. Rom. 13. 13. <hi>Let us work honeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as in the Day, not in Rioting and Drunkenneſs, not in Chambering and Wantonneſs, not in ſtrife and Envy.</hi> There are ſeveral other places I might mention, but theſe may ſuffice; if God would be pleaſed to ſet any one of them with power upon the heart of a Poor Sinner.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:62169:24"/>
Now I ſhall ſpeak a few words to all thoſe that in a great mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure are the cauſes of the growth and increaſe of theſe evils, and they are Magiſtrates, Miniſters, and Parents, and Maſters of Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies. There are ſome Magiſtrates that are ſo far from puniſhing theſe Enormities, that they are Preſidents and ringleaders of all theſe vices, as Swearing, Who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, and Drunkenneſs, nay they are like thoſe ſpoken of by the Prophet. Jer. 3. 12. <hi>Oh my Prophet, they that lead thee cauſe thee to err, and deſtroy the way of thy Paths. verſ.</hi> 13, 14. Surely they are moſt fit to be Magiſtrates ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Scripture, that fear God and hate Covetouſneſs, and every evil way. Oh ſaith the meaner ſort that would have Fig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaves to cover their Nakedneſs, uſe to ſuch a Magiſtrate or Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter, do ſuch things, and they are
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:62169:24"/>
learned, if it were ſo ſinful they would not do it; ſuch kind of Magiſtrates and Miniſters cauſe them to Sin, extenuate and are great examples to encourage to evil. Oh what a ſad thing is this, that men are not content only to go to Hell themſelves but draw others after them, therefore their condemnation will be the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt at the great day of accompt.</p>
               <p>2, <hi>Miniſters,</hi> thoſe that call themſelves Miniſters of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, Oh what wickedneſs are they arrived unto, that ſome of them reel in the Streets; and make nothing of ſwearing, curſing and uncleanneſs; do not you think that Gods Soul will be avenged on ſuch as you are, who are like <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reboams</hi> Prieſts, the vileſt of the People, you that pretend to be leaders of others, ſhould be ſuch bad examples as to lead the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple towards Hell, what will your
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:62169:25"/>
accompt be when both Miniſters and Magiſtrates ſhall appear be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the judgment ſeat of Jeſus Chriſt, what can you ſay here, am I one of thoſe have lead to Hell, ſurely your condemnation will be very great, that will not only an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer for your own Sins, but for o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, whom you have by evil examples drawn to Sin; how can you bear the weight of this great burthen of Judgments that will certainly fall upon you, if you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent not and turn to the Lord ſpeedily? here I might be very large, but I ſhall forbear at this time, hoping that ſome may be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wakened, which is the main end of this ſmall diſcourſe.</p>
               <p>3. To Parents and Maſters of Families, who are very bad preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents to their Wives, Children &amp; Servants, who are ſo far from in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructing them in the ways of God, according to gods injunction in
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:62169:25"/>
the holy Scriptures, that they are the Ring-leaders of them to all manner of evil, Oh ſinful Parents and Maſters, that ſhould with all your might inſtruct your Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren and Servants, how will you, how can you eſcape great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation, when you ſhall be call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to a ſtrict accompt for leading your Children and Servants to great deſtruction, how ſad will it be with you, when your Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren and Servants ſhall curſe you, and ſay we might have eſcaped theſe flames had our Maſters and Parents inſtr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cted us, and had they not been wicked examples to us, but now wo and alas we are tormented with the Devil and his Angels in everlaſting burnings.</p>
               <p>Now let me give you a few in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uctions to poor Sin-ſinking <hi>England,</hi> I beſeech you hearken to the counſels of Gods holy word
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:62169:26"/>
when he threatned deſtruction upon the People of <hi>Iſarel.</hi> Joel. 2. from the 1. to the 22. verſ. <hi>Blow the Trumpet in</hi> Zion <hi>and ſound an alarum in my holy moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, let all the Inhabitants trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, for the day of the Lord cometh, for it is nigh at hand, a day of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and gloomineſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, a day of clouds and thick darkneſs, as the Morning ſpread upon the mountains, a great People and a ſtrong, there hath not been ever the like, neither ſhall be any more after i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, even to the years of many Generations.</hi> verſ. the 3. <hi>A fire devoureth before them, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind them a flame burneth, the land is as the Garden of</hi> Eden, <hi>before them and behind them a d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſolate Wilderneſs, yea nothing ſhall eſcape them,</hi> and ſo forward to the 12. <hi>verſ.</hi> but conſider in the 12, 13, 14. <hi>verſes,</hi> you have that bleſſed counſel given to them as the only means to eſcape this dreadful
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:62169:26"/>
judgment, where you have very much of the bowels of Gods com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion expreſſed like a tender hearted Father, unwilling to ſtrike, if it may be avoided. <hi>Therefore alſo now ſaith the Lord, turn ye e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven unto me with all your heart, and with Faſting, and with Weeping, and with Mourning.</hi> verſ. the 13. <hi>And rent your hearts and not your Garments, and turn unto the Lord your God, for he is gracious, merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, ſlow to anger, and of great kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and repenteth him of the evil.</hi> verſ. the 14. <hi>Who knoweth if he will return and leave a bleſſing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind him, even a meat offering and a drink offering to the Lord your God;</hi> and ſo you may read unto the end of the Chapter. Theſe latter verſes have in them contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the forcible arguments to preſs on and enforce the exhortation, ſurely there is no other way for <hi>England</hi> to eſcape total ruin, but
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:62169:27"/>
by following the bleſſed advice, &amp; very wholeſom counſel of repent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and turning to the Lord with your whole hearts, and who is able to give us counſel that may do us good but God, whoſe coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel ſhall we adhere unto that may be effectual but his, but if we ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinately perſiſt in the rebellions againſt the great God of heaven, he will ſurely plague us ſeven times more for our Sins, and ſo may root us out from being a people, now the Cup of tremble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by our neighbour nations, who knows but we may drink the dregs and bottoms of the Cup that ſuch a ſtubborn, impudent, brazen-fac'd, rebellious People, as have ſined againſt ſo much light and love; we know that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratitude is counted one of the worſt evils, as your Latin Phraſe is, <hi>Si dixeris ingratum eſt omne malum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:62169:27"/>
There is no true Chriſtian de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires the evil day, but doth pray earneſtly to your Lord for the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion of his judgments from the Nation, and however they are lightly eſteemed amongſt men, and called Phanaticks, yet they are the pillers of the Earth and the beſt friends to the King and Kingdom, allthough they are ſlighted and perſecuted for clea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving cloſe to Gods word, which they dare not, nor will not ſwarve from what ever they ſuffer, and knowing the terror of the Lord, we do perſwade men to turn from their evil ways to the Lord, that ſo they may not bring ruin upon themſelves and others, ſurely it will be a very terrible day upon all thoſe that perſecute the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God, and I pray you what do you perſecute them for, I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive you do not underſtand what is written againſt thoſe that ſit at
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:62169:28"/>
eaſe, and eat the fat, and drink the ſweet, and think they do well if they can procure the Miniſters of the goſpel and Chriſtians to be put in Priſon. But all you that are of that ſpirit to worry the pretious harmleſs Lambs of Jeſus Chriſt, I would not be in your caſes for ten thouſand worlds; mark what our Lord Jeſus ſaith to ſuch; <hi>Mat.</hi> 18. 6. <hi>But whoſo ſhall offend one of theſe little ones, which beleive in me; it were better a mil-ſtone were hanged about his neck, &amp; that he were drown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the depth of the ſea.</hi> Mar. 9. 42. Luk. 17. 1, 2.</p>
               <p>And thus I conclude with my earneſt prayers to the God of all grace and mercy, beſeeching him rather to glorify his mercy in the reformation of this poor ſinful Iſland, then his Juſtice in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion and deſolation of it, now as I was concluding, I was look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for that place of Scripture
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:62169:28"/>
In Jer. <hi>Where the Prophet ſaith Lord thou knoweſt I do not deſire the evilday.</hi> Theſe Scriptures were preſented unto my view, Jer. 18. from the 9. to the 12. verſ. <hi>And at what inſtant I ſhall ſpeak concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Nation, and concerning a Kingdom, to build and to plant it,</hi> verſ. the 10. <hi>If it do evil in my ſight, and obey not my voice, then will I repent of the good wherewith I ſaid I will benefit them.</hi> verſ. the 11. <hi>Now therefore go to ſpeak to the men of</hi> Judah, <hi>and to the Inhabitants of</hi> Jeruſalem, <hi>ſaying, thus ſaith the Lord, behold I frame evil againſt you, and deviſe a device againſt you; return ye every one from the evil of his way, and make your ways and your doings good.</hi> Chap. 13. 18, 19. <hi>Say unto the King and to the Queen humble your ſelves, ſit down, for your Principalities ſhall come down, even the Crown of your glory.</hi> verſ. the 19. to the end of
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:62169:29"/>
that Chapter. <hi>The Citys of the South ſhall be ſhut up,</hi> Judah <hi>ſhall be carryed away Captive, all of it ſhall be wholly carryed away Captive.</hi> Thus you ſee the denuntiation of Gods threatnings of terrible judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments againſt a rebellious Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple that walketh in a way that is not good after their own thoughts. Oh therefore I humbly beſeech you hear and fear, and turn to the Lord with your whole hearts.</p>
               <p>9. <hi>Sin,</hi> That is a Land de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroying Sin, is Sabbath breaking, which is firſt a breach of the 4th Commandment. Exod. 20. 8. <hi>Remember the Sabbath day to keep it holy.</hi> This is the law that was given in thundering and light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning. Exod. 19. 16. <hi>And it came to paſs the third day in the Morning that there were thundrings and light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings, ſo that all the people that were in the Camp trembled.</hi> One reaſon may be why the Law was given
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:62169:29"/>
in that terrible manner, that the people might fear to break that righteous Law, for that God which ſhewed himſelf terrible in the giving of the Law, can alſo ſhew himſelf as terrible on them that violate this righteous Law, which appoints a time for his worſhip, in pouring down his wrath and indignation upon Nations that break this righteous and juſt Law, ſo that if there be a God to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, (as doubtleſs there is) and certainly there is a time that he hath ſet apart; which ought to be kept holy, then wo be to all thoſe that dare adventure to prophain his holy day, as in this well go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern'd City and in the Suburbs thereof, is Coſter-Mongers and others ſelling their fruit on that holy day, and other things on that day: Friends it is not altogether ſo much the matter done which maketh the breach of the Sabbath,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:62169:30"/>
as any thing done which ought not to be done, picking of ſticks was but a ſmall buſineſs, and yet ſee how God was diſpleaſed, ſee that he deſtroyed thoſe that did it, nothing but works of neceſſity and mercy. Nehem. 10. 13. <hi>And if the people of the Land bring ware or any victuals on the Sabbath day we will not buy it, we will not buy of them on the Sabbath, or on the holy day.</hi> Chapt. 13. from the 15. to the 23. <hi>Where good</hi> Nehemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah <hi>teſtifyed againſt them that ſould victualls.</hi> verſ. the 17. <hi>Then I contended with the Nobles, and ſaid to them, what evil thing is this that ye do and prophane the Sabbath day.</hi> verſ. the 18. <hi>Did not your Fathers thus, and did not our God bring all this evil upon us, upon this City, yet ye bring more wrath by prophaning the Sabbath.</hi> See the Zeal of a good Governor, he contended againſt evil, and encouraged them in
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:62169:30"/>
that which was good, which is the duty of all Magiſtrates; but <hi>è contra</hi> with us in <hi>England,</hi> there be ſome Magiſtrates that diſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage vertue and encourage vice, what a ſad thing is this, thoſe Magiſtrates that do ſo are not appointed nor ſet up. Exod. 16. 23. Chapt. 31. 15. <hi>Six days may work be done, but in the 7th is the Sabbath of reſt, holy to the Lord, whoſoever doth any work on the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath, he ſhall ſurely be put to death.</hi> ſo in the 14. verſ. Chapt. 35. 2. Levit. 23. 2. Num. 15. 32, 34. verſ. the 35. <hi>And the Lord ſaid unto</hi> Moſes, <hi>the man ſhall be ſurely put to death, and the Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation ſhall ſtone him with ſtones.</hi> and verſ. 36. <hi>And they ſtoned him with ſtones and he dyed, as the Lord commanded Moſes. Deut.</hi> 5. 12, 13, 14. <hi>John</hi> 20. 19. <hi>Eſ.</hi> 56. 2. 6. And thus you ſee the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures Enjoyning us to keep the
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:62169:31"/>
Lords day, and the denuntiation of threatnings againſt thoſe that break this holy day; although the day be altered from all the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, you may ſafely conclude that there is a time ſet a part by God for his worſhip and ſervice, and if the leaſt breach were pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed with death, what ſhall be the violation of the whole day, and that is much by traveling on the Lords day, which is the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket day of your Soules, and do you think a wiſe man will be diverted from his Markets by trifling gewgaws, eſpecially when his livelyhood lyeth upon it; a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother way how Perſons break the Sabbath is by ſpending their time in needleſs adornments of the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, &amp; after Sermon either to ſtand gazeing at their Doores, or talk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing impertinently contrary to the work of the day, of worldly things, of vain and laſcivious things, and
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:62169:31"/>
how doſt thou reſt when thou art imployed with thy thoughts and tongue, though thou art not with thy hands, which is as it were one and the ſame, for when the heart is gone from the ſervice of God all your life is gone, and there is little leſt but a dead Carkaſe, which is no Keeping of a day to the Lord. Another way how Perſons break the Lords day, that after ſeveral Gentry and others have careleſly heard the word, then they muſt recreate themſelves by walking in <hi>Grays-Inn</hi> walks or in the Fields, with vain and unſavory diſcourſes, and ſo Sathan ſteales the word they have heard, and they are ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the better, but as ready to go to their Luſts all the Week after, and ſo drive a ſad trade of Sin which brings great judgments, Temporal, Spiritual and Eternal. I might urge many Scriptures both in the Old and New Teſtament,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:62169:32"/>
and ſeveral Arguments might b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> produced, but famous Mr. <hi>Dod,</hi> that worthy ſervant of Jeſus Chriſt, and others have done ſo learnedly, that it is but the Widdows mite that I can caſt into the treaſury by way of confirmation of what hath been formerly ſpoken, I ſhall end this particular, with two things, firſt to ſhew you briefly how the Sabbath ought to be kept, and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly ſpeak ſomthing of the al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teration of the day.</p>
               <p>1. How a Sabbath day of reſt ought to be kept holy, remember to keep holy the Sabbath day, it is ſet a part from all ſervicable works, but works of mercy and neceſſity may be done; thou art to prepare to keep the Lords day. Secondly begin in the Morning withprivate Prayers &amp; meditation, pray for the preſence of God in all his ordinances, praiſe God for the great work of redemption, and for
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:62169:32"/>
the reſurrection, for in that day Jeſus Chriſt roſe from the dead, and now ſits at the right hand of that glorious place on high, ever living to make interce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſion for all that believe. Secondly bleſs God for his holy word, and beg that it may be to thee as it was to <hi>David</hi> ſweeter then hony and the hony<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comb, and that it may be ſo bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, that it may do thy Soul good, and that the inſtructions of the word may teach thee, and the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehentions of the Word to weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en Sin in thee, and that the exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations may perſwade thee, and the conſolations comfort thee, and when thou haſt been hearing the word thou muſt examine what word it was that met with thy Soul, and make much of that, and if thou wouldeſt ſpend thy time in hearing and praying and praiſing their would be no ſpare time for walking up and down unneſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily.
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:62169:33"/>
Now to you that are Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of Families, it is your duty to pray privately to your Families every day, but begin with prayer on the Lords day in the Morning, and then pray with thy Family, and ſo bring thy Children and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants to the hearing of the word powerfully preached, and after repeat, and ſo to Prayer, and thus ſpend the Lords day in holy exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſes, then thou wilt undoubted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be more ſit to ſerve God in thy particular calling in the Week, and then thou maiſt expect a bleſſing from heaven upon all thou haſt, for it is the bleſſing of God maketh rich, and addeth no ſorrow with it.</p>
               <p>But thoſe Scriptures that you have brought are for keeping of the ſeventh day. It is true, the ſeventh day was the Jewiſh Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath, but we find a change of the day after the reſurrection, and the
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:62169:33"/>
goſpel ordinances were admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred on that day, it was that day in which Jeſus Chriſt roſe from the dead, we ſee what Chriſt ſaith <hi>Math.</hi> the 12. from the 1. to the 9. <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> 20. 7. <hi>Rev.</hi> 1. 10. It is ſaid that ſome greek Coppies do render it thus, <hi>John</hi> was raviſhed in the Spirit on the Lords, day be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the firſt day of the Week, but I am not now to intermeddle with that controverſie, but am fully ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfyed in my own mind, that there is ſufficient warrant in the New Teſtament for keeping the firſt day of the Week or Lords day, in which we are to celebrate the praiſes of God in the great work of redemption.</p>
               <p>10. Sin, Which is a Land de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroying Sin, is Covetouſneſs and oppreſſion, firſt covetouſneſs is a greedy deſire of that which is none of their own, ſecondly cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſs is againſt the righteous
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:62169:34"/>
Law of God. In Exod. 20. 17. Hebrews. 13. and the 5. <hi>Let your converſations be without covetouſneſs, and be content with thoſe things that you have.</hi> 3. Col. 5. 6. <hi>Mortify therefore your members which are up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Earth; Fornication, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nclean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Inordinate affection, evil con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupiſcence and covetouſneſs which is Idolatry, for which things ſake the Wrath of God cometh on the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of diſobedience.</hi> See Eſ. 57. 17. <hi>For the Iniquity of his cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſs I was wrath and ſmote him.</hi> Several Scriptures that reprehend this evil, and Arguments might be urged, but in regard many worthy Servants of Jeſus Chriſt have demonſtrated this evil of Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetouſneſs at large, I ſhall as it were but briefly touch upon it, &amp; ſpeak ſomething to that which is obvious to the practice of the men of our age, it very much re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehends ſome trades men and
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:62169:34"/>
Uſerers, that when men that have got into their debt, they feed them with mony, and ſo on a ſudden call for their Debt, and if the Debtor hath not mony to pay, then they muſt have a Mortgage upon his Land, and if it be not redeemed in ſuch a fixt time, then they ceaſe upon the Land for half the worth of it, and ſo they ruin them and their Poſterity, although it is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry true that every man ought to pay his Debt, but the Creditor muſt not raiſe it in a Siniſter way, Preying upon others neceſſities, and taking advantage upon men when they are in a Low condition but it is honeſt, to give every one the full value of his Land, as any other Purchaſer would do, but they have clandeſtine wayes to eat up mens Eſtates, before they are aware, and ſo forcibly throw them out; this is a horrible ſhame, and a great fruit of covetouſneſs, and
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:62169:35"/>
that which the Creditor gets by ſuch ways will conſume as But<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in the Sun, for God will blaſt, and not bleſs, what is contrary to his will.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>2ly.</hi> I ſhall briefly ſhew you how covetouſneſs may be ſaid to be Idolatry; f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r whatever thou loveſt or truſteſt in more than God, that undoubtedly thou ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keſt thy God. For conſider if a man have loſt a beaſt or any out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward thing, how exceedingly will he complain and bewail his loſs, but when thou loſeſt the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of God and the enjoyment of communion with himſelf thou makeſt no matter of that which is the cheifeſt good, and ſurely this is a clear demonſtration that thou loveſt theſe creatures more than the Creator bleſſed for ever.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>2ly.</hi> That which thou art ſo much caſt down in the abſence, and ſo exceedingly lifted up and
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:62169:35"/>
rejoycing in the preſence of, and in the enjoyment, muſt needs be thy chiefeſt delight, and ſo cloſeſt with thy Idol, inſtead of the true God, and in this thou art certainly to blame.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>2ly.</hi> Oppreſſion, when men op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs the poor and needy. <hi>Pſa.</hi> 12. 5. <hi>For the oppreſsion of the Poor, for the ſighing of the needy, now will I a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe ſaith the Lord, I will ſet him in ſafety from him that puffeth at him.</hi> The rich oppreſs the poor, as Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters oppreſs their ſervants and prentices, and Magiſtrates oppreſs their ſubjects. Then Maſters op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs their ſervants, when they do not that which is equal to them, they break the Royal Rule, do as you wou'd bedon by. For Maſters to detein their ſervants wages, and not to give that which is neceſſary and convenient for them, this is a great oppreſſion. See <hi>Job</hi> 35. 9. <hi>By reaſon of the multitude of oppreſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi>
                  <pb n="64" facs="tcp:62169:36"/>
                  <hi>they make the oppreſſed to cry, they cry out by reaſon of the arme of the Mighty.</hi> Eccleſ. 4. 1. <hi>So I returned and conſidered all the oppreſsions that are done under the Sun, and behold the tears of ſuch as are oppreſſed, and they had no comforter, and on the ſide of their oppreſſors there was power; but they had no comforter.</hi> Iſ. 33. 15. So when Governors of Nations lay any heavy burthens upon the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple contrary to the rule of Gods word, and contrary to the Law of the Nation, this is great oppreſſion as <hi>Pharaoh</hi> made the people make Brick without ſtraw. See <hi>Exod.</hi> 5. from the 7. to the 19. verſ. 15. <hi>Then the Officers of the Children of Iſrael cryed unto Pharaoh, ſaying, wherefore dealeſt thou thus with thy ſervants, there is no ſtraw given un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thy ſervants, and they ſay unto us make Brick, and behold thy ſervants are beaten, but the fault is in thy own people,</hi> verſ. 17. <hi>But he ſaid ye are</hi>
                  <pb n="65" facs="tcp:62169:36"/>
                  <hi>idle, ye are idle, therefore ye ſay let us go and do ſacrifice unto the Lord.</hi> ver. 18. <hi>Go therefore now and worke, for there ſhall no ſtraw be given you, yet ſhall ye deliver the tale of bricks.</hi> Job 15. 20. With many other places I might alledge. So that you may ſee, how oppreſſors have been formerly, &amp; ſo are to this day, and how the holy Scriptures condemn that ſin, and it brings judgments upon the guilty, on them and their poſterity. Therefore repent of this great, unlovely, uncharitable, ſelf-deſtroying ſin; for elſe it will bring the ſwift judgments of God upon all thoſe that practiſe this a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bominable evil, both upon them and their poſterity. See <hi>Job</hi> 57. from the 13, to the end of the chapt. <hi>This is the portion of wicked men with God, and the heritage which they ſhall receive of the Almighty; if his children be multiplied, it is for the ſword, and his off-spring ſhall not be</hi>
                  <pb n="66" facs="tcp:62169:37"/>
                  <hi>ſatisfied.</hi> verſ. the 15. <hi>Thoſe that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main of him ſhall be buried in death, and his widdows ſhall not weep.</hi> verſ. the 20. <hi>Terrors take hold on him as waters, a tempeſt ſtealeth him away in the night.</hi> 21. <hi>The Eaſt-wind car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rieth him away and he departeth, and as a ſtorm hurleth him out of his place.</hi> 22. <hi>For God ſhall caſt upon him and not ſpare, he wou'd fain flee out of his hands.</hi> 23. <hi>Men ſhall clap their hands at him. and ſhall hiſs him out of his place.</hi> And this is the portion of wicked men from the Lord. I beſeech you, let every one exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine himſelf whether he be not guilty of this ſin. <hi>Prov.</hi> 3. 31. and 28. 16. <hi>Jer.</hi> 21. 12. and 22. 3. And ſee the danger of and avoid it, and turn to the Lord from every evil way, that ſo iniquity may not be your ruin.</p>
               <p>11. Sin, is the ſin of Profeſſors that profeſs Religion, and do not practiſe what you profeſs. Surely
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:62169:37"/>
when we make a ſcrutiny into our own hearts, and behold the prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe of other Profeſſors; it is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently to be demonſtrated, that there is ſo little love to God and Jeſus Chriſt, that have deſerved all our love; that we may be aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med. See what little love there is to Saints, that bear the Image of Chriſt. Surely we are fallen into the latter days that our Lord Jeſus ſpeaks of, <hi>Math.</hi> 24. 12. <hi>And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe iniquity abounds, the love of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſhall wax cold.</hi> The great reaſon that Chriſt gives why the love of many waxeth cold, is becauſe ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity abounds. Therefore now it muſt needs wax cold, becauſe there was never greater abounding of iniquity in all ſorts as at this day. There is no man that loves God aright, but he muſt love his Image where ever he ſee it. 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 2. from the 9. to the 12. Loving our Brethren is made a certain cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:62169:38"/>
of a Chriſtian. 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3. 10. and 4. 20. that Epiſtle is ſpent in treating of Faith and Love. And therefore I deſire all Chriſtians ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly to read and weigh thoſe five chapt. of 1. of John, it doth very much reprehend our defects in this thing eſpecially; and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horts all to believe. Oh examine thy heart, and be earneſt at the throne of grace, that God wou'd make thee ſincere, that thou mayſt avoid the evils of the day thou li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt in, and do the duties of the day, which is eſpecially (1) Love to God and Jeſus Chriſt, (2) Love to the Saints; (3) Watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs and keeping thy garments clean, leſt thou be found naked, I ſhall end with this Scripture which is our Lord Jeſus's reprehenſion of and counſel to, the Church of <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſus,</hi> Rev. 2. 4, 5. <hi>Nevertheleſs I have ſomewhat againſt thee, becauſe thou haſt left thy firſt love: Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber</hi>
                  <pb n="69" facs="tcp:62169:38"/>
                  <hi>therefore from whence thou art fallen, and repent, and do thy firſt works; or elſe I will come againſt thee and remove thy Candleſtick out of his place, except thou repent.</hi> Oh let us every one conſider what is ſaid, and the Lord give a right under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding in all things. Oh the lukewarmneſs and want of love to God, and Chriſt, and Saints. Oh the carnality of Profeſſors: a <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>odicean</hi> frame, is the worſt frame in profeſſors. Mark what the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God ſaith in the 3 of the <hi>Re.</hi> 3. <hi>And unto the Angel of the Church of Laodicea write theſe things ſaith the Amen, the faithful and true wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, the Beginning of the Creation of God.</hi> verſ. 15. <hi>I know thy works that thou art neither hot nor cold, ſo becauſe thou art lukewarm, and nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther cold nor hot, I will ſpue thee out of my mouth.</hi> Are not your expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions very great, the accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of all thoſe faithful promiſes
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:62169:39"/>
which God hath made in theſe lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter days; and therefore Chriſtians ſhould be diligent, and be up and doing, and be ſervent in the ſpirit, ſerving the Lord with much vigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancy and ſincerity; preparing for the day of the Lord which draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth nigh: <hi>And bleſſed are all thoſe ſervants, whom their Lord ſhall find doing their Maſters will; he will make them ſit down and he will ſerve them.</hi> Take heed of ſpiritual pride for that poyſons Angelical perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ions. Take heed of a carnal, formal frame of ſpirit, for that will make thee unfit for doing or ſuffering. <hi>Oh awake thou that ſleepeſt, and riſe from the dead and Chriſt ſhall give thee life:</hi> for thou haſt a great work to do and a very little time to do it; and therefore up and be doing, and the Lord be with thee. Labour to exerciſe faith and patience, faith in God, and love to God, and
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:62169:39"/>
very much longing and ardent de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire after <hi>God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>2. A patient wayting for <hi>God, For he that ſhall come, will come and will not tarry, but the Juſt ſhall live by faith; but if any man draw back, my ſoul ſhall have no pleaſure in him,</hi> Heb. 10. 35, 36, 37, 38. Now with my earneſt prayers at the Throne of grace for you, deſiring the <hi>God</hi> of all grace and rich mercy, to preſerve us blameleſs, and to keep us by his mighty power through faith to ſalvation: that we over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come to the death, and ſo enjoy a Crown of life; which the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Lord will aſſuredly give to all thoſe that love and long for his appearance.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
